<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ovids remedy of love directing lovers how they may by reason suppresse the passion of love.</title>
            <title>Remedia amoris. English</title>
            <author>Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18976.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">25213224</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 25213224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27887</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08668)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27887)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1857:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ovids remedy of love directing lovers how they may by reason suppresse the passion of love.</title>
                  <title>Remedia amoris. English</title>
                  <author>Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith, and are to be sold at his shop neare Holburne Conduit, at the signe of the Sunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁷ B⁸ C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27887:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27887:1"/>
            <p>OVIDS REMEDY Of Love.</p>
            <p>DIRECTING Lovers how they may by Reaſon ſuppreſſe the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>— Nunc ego mitibus</l>
               <l>Mutare quaero triſtia.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor.</hi> Ode <hi>16.</hi> Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neare <hi>Holburne Conduit,</hi> at the ſigne of the Sunne. 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:27887:2"/>
            <head>On the Author and Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOve</hi> being of a gentle diſpoſition,</l>
               <l>Was mov'd by Lovers ſighes unto contrition:</l>
               <l>So that the ſweet-ſtrain'd <hi>Ovid</hi> he inſpires</l>
               <l>With a ſof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhowre to quench thoſe amorous fires</l>
               <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e up by his <hi>Art of Love,</hi> ſo that you ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Love</hi> hath prepar'd for <hi>Love a Remedy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wandring <hi>Aeneas</hi> talk't the faire Queene <hi>Dide</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Love,</hi> and after cur'd the Royall Widdow</l>
               <l>Within a Cave: Our <hi>Poet</hi> doth approve</l>
               <l>A chaſter way in's <hi>Remedy of Love,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cloſing thoſe wounds that did before he open,</l>
               <l>In ſuch ſort, that no Maidenhead ſhall be broken.</l>
               <l>He wipeth teares from the ſad Lovers eyes,</l>
               <l>And does inſtruct him wittily to deſpiſe</l>
               <l>His Miſtreſſe ſcorne, and all in Lines ſo ſweete,</l>
               <l>That every leafe may be <hi>Loves</hi> winding-ſheete.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27887:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>OVIDS</hi> Remedy of Love.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>Liber</hi> 1.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Love</hi> the Title of this booke had read,</l>
                  <l>Wars againſt me (ſaith he) are threatened.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> doe not condemn him of that crime</l>
                  <l>Who is thy <hi>Poet,</hi> and hath many a time</l>
                  <l>Borne up thoſe colours thou deliverd'ſt me,</l>
                  <l>And for my guide and Captaine followed thee.</l>
                  <l>I am not fierce <hi>Tydides</hi> who did wound</l>
                  <l>Thy Mother <hi>Venus,</hi> ſo that in a ſwound</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Mars</hi> his Chariot ſhe was found to fly,</l>
                  <l>And returne to Heaven through the moiſtned skie.</l>
                  <l>Some young men are in love but for a time,</l>
                  <l>But I to love doe alwaies ſtill incline:</l>
                  <l>And if you would know now what I doe doe,</l>
                  <l>I muſt confeſſe, I am in love now too.</l>
                  <l>Though I did once ſuch Rules of love impart,</l>
                  <l>As did reduce that paſſion to an Art.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27887:3"/>I will not now betray thee gentle <hi>Boy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor yet my <hi>Art of Love</hi> will I deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>That which I in my former worke have done,</l>
                  <l>By my new <hi>Muſe</hi> ſhall not now be unſpun.</l>
                  <l>If any one doe love, and love aright,</l>
                  <l>Placing his love where it doth yeeld delight,</l>
                  <l>Affording ſweet contentment to his mind,</l>
                  <l>Let him proceed ſtill with a proſperous wind.</l>
                  <l>But if any one love a diſdainfull Maid,</l>
                  <l>Then by this Art his griefe ſhall be allay'd:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Rules if he peruſe, he ſhall not dye</l>
                  <l>For her diſdaine, or ſcornefull cruelty.</l>
                  <l>For why ſhould Lovers whom love doth entangle,</l>
                  <l>Themſelves ſo often with a halter ſtrangle?</l>
                  <l>Why with their daggers ſhould they ſtab their breſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Love,</hi> thou art blam'd who loveſt peace and reſt.</l>
                  <l>Let him ceaſe to love, who needs for love will dye,</l>
                  <l>Be not thou Author of his Tragedy.</l>
                  <l>Thou art a Boy, and unto ſport ſhouldſt runne,</l>
                  <l>And a ſoft government doth thy yeeres become.</l>
                  <l>Thou mayſt uſe naked arrows in the Warres,</l>
                  <l>But thy gult Darts doe leave no mortall skarres.</l>
                  <l>Let others in Swords and in ſhaipe ſpeares delight,</l>
                  <l>And get the victory by a bloody fight.</l>
                  <l>Reverence thou thy mothers Arts more mild,</l>
                  <l>By which no mother hath loſt her deare childe.</l>
                  <l>By thy powers let the doores at night reſound</l>
                  <l>With knocking, and with flowry wreaths be crown'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27887:3"/>Let fearefull Mayds and young men by ſtealth meet,</l>
                  <l>Let wives their wary husbands finely cheat,</l>
                  <l>Make the Lover flatter at the doore, and chide,</l>
                  <l>While he ſhut out doth ſinging there abide.</l>
                  <l>To ſee their teares, not death ſhould make thee smile</l>
                  <l>Thy Torch is unfit to light a funerall pile.</l>
                  <l>When I had ſpoken thus, golden <hi>Love</hi> diſplay'd</l>
                  <l>His Pearle-embroidred wings, and to me ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Finiſh thy worke which thou haſt now begun,</l>
                  <l>And you deceiv'd young men unto me come,</l>
                  <l>You that love hath deceiv'd in every kind.</l>
                  <l>Here by my precepts you ſome helpe ſhall finde,</l>
                  <l>And learne from him that did the Rules impart</l>
                  <l>Of love, how you may cure your ſelves by Art:</l>
                  <l>That the ſame hand which wounded you, againe</l>
                  <l>May heale you, and may mitigate your paine.</l>
                  <l>The earth both wholeſome hearbs &amp; weeds doth che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</l>
                  <l>And by the Roſe the Nettle oft doth flouriſh.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Pelias</hi> Speare ſuch virtue did conceale,</l>
                  <l>That it would make a wound, and it would heale.</l>
                  <l>To men and maydens I declare my Art,</l>
                  <l>Striving to arme them both in every part:</l>
                  <l>Wherein if ſome things not ſo uſefull be,</l>
                  <l>Yet by example you the way may ſee:</l>
                  <l>My purpoſe is good, to quench Loves cruell flame,</l>
                  <l>That no vice in thy ſervile breſt may reigne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phyllis</hi> had liv'd, if ſhee had ruled beene</l>
                  <l>By thoſe precepts which may here be read, and ſeene.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27887:4"/>Nor dying <hi>Dido</hi> had not ſeene that houre,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe beheld from the top of her Towre</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Trojan</hi> ſhips, that would no longer ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Hoiſt up their ſayles, and forthwith ſteale away,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Progne</hi> with her ſorrow growing wilde,</l>
                  <l>To vexe her husband had not kild her childe.</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Philomela Tereus</hi> did pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>My Art had helpt him, and cur'd his diſeaſe:</l>
                  <l>So that he had not merited to be</l>
                  <l>Transform'd to a bird for his impiety.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paſiphae</hi> had not a Bull affected,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phaedra</hi> had her filthy love neglected,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Menelaus</hi> had his <hi>Helena</hi> enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>Nor by the <hi>Grecians</hi> had <hi>Troy</hi> beene deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>If wicked <hi>Scylla</hi> this booke had but read,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Niſus</hi> purple haire had ſtill growne on his head.</l>
                  <l>Let loſing lovers learne how to aſſwage,</l>
                  <l>By my inſtruction their loves furious rage,</l>
                  <l>That their ſhip with the reſt ſaile fairely on,</l>
                  <l>While I their faithfull guide and Pilot am.</l>
                  <l>You ſhould have <hi>Ovid</hi> read when you begun</l>
                  <l>To love, and now you may read him againe:</l>
                  <l>For I will helpe him whom love doth oppreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Then favour him that helpes you in diſtreſſe.</l>
                  <l>And I intreate thee now when I begin,</l>
                  <l>Even thee <hi>Apollo,</hi> whoſe brow is hem'd in</l>
                  <l>With the greene Laurell, thou that didſt invent</l>
                  <l>Both Verſe and Phyſick, further my intent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:27887:4"/>Helpe thou thy Poet playing the Phyſitian,</l>
                  <l>Both which Arts belong unto thy juriſdiction.</l>
                  <l>When Sun-light motions doe affection ſtirre,</l>
                  <l>Stay them before that they doe goe too farre.</l>
                  <l>Quench thoſe new flames before they gather force,</l>
                  <l>And ſtop in the beginning of thy courſe.</l>
                  <l>Time and delay doe bring the imperfect ſhapes</l>
                  <l>Of deſire to ripeneſſe, as time ripens Grapes:</l>
                  <l>And which was a tender blade in ſhow,</l>
                  <l>In time unto an eare of corne doth grow.</l>
                  <l>The tree that doth afford a ſpreading ſhade</l>
                  <l>To thoſe that walke or underneath are laid.</l>
                  <l>Like to a ſmall twig at firſt it did appeare,</l>
                  <l>At what time it was ſet or planted there,</l>
                  <l>Then it might have beene pluckt up with our hands,</l>
                  <l>Now bigger growne it firmely rooted ſtands.</l>
                  <l>Conſider firſt what ſhe is thou doſt love,</l>
                  <l>And from the galling yoake thy necke remove.</l>
                  <l>"Prevent beginnings, Phyſicks are too late at longth,</l>
                  <l>"When thy ſickneſſe by delay hath gatherd ſtrength.</l>
                  <l>Make haſte, in good things alwayes ſhun delay.</l>
                  <l>"He'le be unfit to morrow, that's unfit to day.</l>
                  <l>Love flatrers us, and is nouriſht by delay,</l>
                  <l>If you would ſhake it off, ſhake it off to day.</l>
                  <l>You ſhall ſee few rivers that from great ſprings flow,</l>
                  <l>But as they run they ſtill more larger grow.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Myrrha!</hi> hadſt thou ſoone perceivd thy ſinne,</l>
                  <l>To a <hi>Myrrh-tree</hi> thou hadſt not transformed beene.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:27887:5"/>I have ſeene a wound that curable did ſeeme</l>
                  <l>At firſt, yet by delay hath worſer beene.</l>
                  <l>Yet becauſe we doe take delight to gather</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Venus</hi> flowers, we doe deferre it rather,</l>
                  <l>And flattering of our ſelves, we ſtill doe ſay,</l>
                  <l>We'le doe to morrow as we did to day.</l>
                  <l>While ſecret flames into our hearts doe creepe,</l>
                  <l>And ill affections there are rooted deepe.</l>
                  <l>But if thou letſt the firſt time ſlippe and periſh,</l>
                  <l>And that thy breaſt an ancient flame doth cheriſh;</l>
                  <l>The work's the greater, yet in helpleſſe ſtate</l>
                  <l>I'le not leave him, though I'me cald ſomewhat too late.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Paeancian</hi> Heroe ſhould have with al ſpeed</l>
                  <l>Cut off that part whence his wound did proceed.</l>
                  <l>Yet many yeares afterward, as it then ſeem'd,</l>
                  <l>Being cur'd, he brought thoſe warres unto an end.</l>
                  <l>I that can cure Love, when it firſt doth grow,</l>
                  <l>When Love doth older waxe the cure is ſlow.</l>
                  <l>Strive at the firſt to quench thy wanton flame,</l>
                  <l>Or when the ſtrength of it is ſpent againe.</l>
                  <l>At firſt yeeld to it, let it take its courſe,</l>
                  <l>It's hard to reſiſt a violent force.</l>
                  <l>He is a foole that againſt the ſtreame will row,</l>
                  <l>Or ſwimme, when as he round about may goe.</l>
                  <l>"The impatient minde will no impreſſion take,</l>
                  <l>"All admonitions it doth ſcorne and hate.</l>
                  <l>"I'le goe to him, when I his wounds may open,</l>
                  <l>"When he'le endure to heare truth when'tis ſpoken.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27887:5"/>While that a mother doth the funerals keepe</l>
                  <l>Of her ſonne, who will forbid her then to weepe,</l>
                  <l>Unleſſe it be one that is voyd of reaſon?</l>
                  <l>For then to admoniſh her is out of ſeaſon.</l>
                  <l>But when ſhe with teares hath eaſed her ſick minde,</l>
                  <l>Then her griefe may by words ſome comfort finde.</l>
                  <l>"Phyſicke in ſeaſon given doth availe;</l>
                  <l>"But given unſeaſonably, hurts without faile.</l>
                  <l>"You ſtrengthen vice, while you ſeeke to redreſſe it,</l>
                  <l>"If you ſtrive out of ſeaſon to ſuppreſſe it.</l>
                  <l>Therefore when thou art curable by Art,</l>
                  <l>This Rule I firſt of all to thee impart.</l>
                  <l>I admoniſh thee moſt carefully to ſhun</l>
                  <l>Idleneſſe, whence all wicked thoughts doe come.</l>
                  <l>This makes thee love, and doth that love maintaine;</l>
                  <l>This cauſes, and doth feed that prety paine.</l>
                  <l>Take away idleneſſe, and <hi>Cupids</hi> dart</l>
                  <l>Hath then no power at all to wound the heart.</l>
                  <l>His Torch hath then no flame or light, but lies</l>
                  <l>Contemn'd, and every one doth it deſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>As the <hi>Popler,</hi> and <hi>Oſier</hi> love the Rivers banke,</l>
                  <l>And the marſh reed loves a muddy ſoile that's rank,</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Venus</hi> in ſoft eaſe doth take much pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>Then let ſome buſineſſe give thy thoughts no leaſure,</l>
                  <l>If to expell Loves paſſion thou deſire,</l>
                  <l>For buſineſſe maketh Loves flame ſoone expire;</l>
                  <l>Soft eaſe, and ſpending as thou liſt the time</l>
                  <l>In ſleeping, and immoderate drinking Wine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27887:6"/>Weakens the mind, and maketh it decay:</l>
                  <l>For treacherous Love the unwary doth betray.</l>
                  <l>"Love haunts the ſlothfull, hates thoſe he doth finde</l>
                  <l>Bufie, then give imployment to thy minde.</l>
                  <l>Goe to the Courts, and heare how they doe plead,</l>
                  <l>Study Law, or elſe for thy friend intercede:</l>
                  <l>Sometimes goe forth, and walke into the Towne,</l>
                  <l>Or behold the trainings of the City-gowne:</l>
                  <l>Or practiſe bloody <hi>Mars</hi> his youthfull Art,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe conceits of Love will ſoone depart.</l>
                  <l>Goe to the Warres, where <hi>Caeſars</hi> troopes doe lie,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt the <hi>Parthians</hi> to obtaine a victory:</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Cupids</hi> and the <hi>Parthian</hi> ſhafts orecome,</l>
                  <l>And bring two Trophies to thy Country home.</l>
                  <l>Why <hi>Aegiſthus</hi> was a murderer wouldſt thou know?</l>
                  <l>The cauſe was, becauſe he did idle grow.</l>
                  <l>Others were fighting at the ſiege of <hi>Troy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Greece</hi> with all her force ſought to deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>Would he follow Warres, at <hi>Argos</hi> none then were,</l>
                  <l>The Courts of Law at <hi>Argos</hi> empty were:</l>
                  <l>So that he lov'd when nought elſe could be done:</l>
                  <l>For love from idleneſſe doth alwayes come.</l>
                  <l>The Country and Husbandry alſo yeeld delight:</l>
                  <l>Theſe cares all other cares doe baniſh quite.</l>
                  <l>Somtimes thou maiſt yoke thy Oxen, and ſo wound</l>
                  <l>With thy crooked ploughſhare the hard clay ground</l>
                  <l>And ſometimes with the Harrow cover o're</l>
                  <l>Thy ſeed, which thy field with intereſt may reſtore.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:27887:6"/>Looke how the crooked boughs bent downwards are</l>
                  <l>With the weight of Apples that are ripe and faire,</l>
                  <l>So that the labouring tree can hardly beare</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fruits which from her firſt produced were.</l>
                  <l>Look how ſoft ſtreames with a ſweet murmur paſſe:</l>
                  <l>Looke how the ſheepe graze on the fruitfull graſſe.</l>
                  <l>Marke how the Goats the ſtony rocks doe climbe,</l>
                  <l>Suckling their Kids when it is evening time;</l>
                  <l>While the Shepheard piping on his reed doth lye,</l>
                  <l>And his watchfull dogges doe beare him company.</l>
                  <l>And then a Cow doth make the woods reſound</l>
                  <l>With lowing for her Calfe as yet unfound.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes you may with ſmoake put under, drive</l>
                  <l>The young brood of Bees out of their waxen hive:</l>
                  <l>And having tooke their Honey got with paine,</l>
                  <l>You may then hive the tender brood againe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Autumne</hi> yeelds apples, <hi>Summer</hi> yeeldeth fruits,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Spring</hi> yeelds flowers, &amp; fire with <hi>Winter</hi> ſuits.</l>
                  <l>The Country-man gathers Grapes at a ſet time,</l>
                  <l>And with naked feet doth preſſe out the new wine.</l>
                  <l>And certaine times he cutteth downe his hay,</l>
                  <l>Rakes it, and makes it, and beares it away.</l>
                  <l>Or in the Garden thou maiſt graft and plant,</l>
                  <l>And water thoſe hearbs which doe watring want.</l>
                  <l>And ſometimes thou maiſt make inciſion,</l>
                  <l>The graft unto the ſtock thereby to joyne,</l>
                  <l>That ſo the ſtock of any home bred tree</l>
                  <l>With outlandiſh boughs and fruit may cover'd be.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:27887:7"/>When theſe pleaſures to thy mind delight do bring,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Love</hi> will fly away on a weake wing.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, thou maiſt ſometimes a hunting run,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> hath oft by <hi>Diana</hi> beene o'recome.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes with Hounds the Hare before thee chaſe,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes thy nets on the ſhady mountaines place.</l>
                  <l>Or purſue the Hart, and put him in a feare,</l>
                  <l>Or wound the Boare with thy ſharp-pointed Speare:</l>
                  <l>That at night thou weary, faſt aſleepe maiſt fall,</l>
                  <l>And of thy Sweet-heart take no care at all.</l>
                  <l>While fatning reſt thy body may refreſh,</l>
                  <l>And baniſh Love which did thy mind oppreſſe.</l>
                  <l>Or thou maiſt take the light-wing'd birds ſometime,</l>
                  <l>Or goe a fiſhing with thy hooke and line:</l>
                  <l>Covering the crooked hook with ſuch a baite,</l>
                  <l>That ſhall make the greedy Fiſh bite at it ſtraight.</l>
                  <l>By theſe and the like wayes untill thou leave</l>
                  <l>To love, thou muſt thy ſelfe thy ſelfe deceive.</l>
                  <l>And if <hi>Loves</hi> fetters thou wouldſt faine off ſhake,</l>
                  <l>Then ſome long journey thou muſt undertake:</l>
                  <l>And though thou weepe for being ſo unkind,</l>
                  <l>When thy Sweet-hearts name doth come into thy mind,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill goe farre from her, goe farre I ſay.</l>
                  <l>And the more thou art unwilling for to goe.</l>
                  <l>Remember to quicken thy pace when 'tis ſlow.</l>
                  <l>Offer violence to thy ſelfe, and ſo goe on,</l>
                  <l>And enforce thy feet away from her to runne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:27887:7"/>Let no light ſhowre of raine thy journey ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Nor the obſervation of an Holy-day:</l>
                  <l>Nor yet enquire how many miles thou haſt gon,</l>
                  <l>But rather enquire how many are to come.</l>
                  <l>Nor poore excuſes, nor delayes doe not faine,</l>
                  <l>That ſomewhat neare to her thou maiſt remaine.</l>
                  <l>Doe not thou reckon the time that is paſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor unto <hi>Rome</hi> a longing looke backe caſt.</l>
                  <l>But ſee that thou doe from her runne and flye,</l>
                  <l>As the <hi>Parthian</hi> would doe from his enemy.</l>
                  <l>Some will ſay my Rules are hard, I know't my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>But thou wilt ſuffer much to gaine thy health.</l>
                  <l>In ſickneſſe I have drunke a bitter juyce,</l>
                  <l>And was deny'd that dyet I would chuſe.</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt endure to be lanchd and ſeard, to regaine</l>
                  <l>Thy bodies health, and canſt from drinke refraine:</l>
                  <l>And to ſuffer any thing wilt thou deny,</l>
                  <l>For thy minds health and her recovery?</l>
                  <l>Since that the minde is a part farre compleater</l>
                  <l>Then any body, and of price farre greater.</l>
                  <l>Though the entrance of my Art ſeeme hard, the firſt</l>
                  <l>"Beginning of a worke ſeemes hard and worſt.</l>
                  <l>At firſt the Heyfer's wrung with the hard yoake,</l>
                  <l>At firſt the ſaddle galleth the ſwift Colt.</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt ſay, it grieves thee to depart from home,</l>
                  <l>Which makes thee to returne when thou art gon.</l>
                  <l>But 'tis thy ſweetharts love thee hom hath brought,</l>
                  <l>While thou with faire words covereſt thy fault.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:27887:8"/>Depart but from her once, and thou ſhalt ſee</l>
                  <l>The Countrey will yeeld comfort unto thee.</l>
                  <l>And the length of the way will helpe to baniſh</l>
                  <l>Thy cares, and company will make it vaniſh.</l>
                  <l>Yet thinke it not enough for to depart</l>
                  <l>From her that is thy Love, and thy Sweet-heart.</l>
                  <l>But thou muſt ſtay from her, till thy deſire</l>
                  <l>Doe loſe its ſtrength, and aſhes hide thy fire.</l>
                  <l>If thou returne before thou haſt quencht thy flame,</l>
                  <l>Rebellious love will aſſault thee againe.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt be what thou wa'ſt, thy love ſhall burne</l>
                  <l>The more by abſence when thou doſt returne.</l>
                  <l>Thinke not if thou inchanted hearbs doſt uſe,</l>
                  <l>And Magicks Arts, they can thy helpe produce.</l>
                  <l>The uſe of charmes is ancient and old,</l>
                  <l>But my harmeleſſe Verſe doth a new way unfold.</l>
                  <l>For I will force no ghoſt his grave to leave,</l>
                  <l>Nor old wife with her charmes the earth ſhall cleave.</l>
                  <l>I will not blaſt the Corne, nor make it faile;</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Phoebus</hi> in his ſphere ſhall not waxe pale.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tyber,</hi> (as he was wont) to the Sea ſhall flow,</l>
                  <l>The Moone be drawne with horſes white as ſnow.</l>
                  <l>I will make thy breſt with charmes lay by</l>
                  <l>Thy cares, nor make ſubdued love to fly.</l>
                  <l>What helpe did enchanted hearbs lend thee or ayd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Medea,</hi> when thou wouldſt at home have ſtaid?</l>
                  <l>And what did <hi>Circe</hi> by her charming Art,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> ſhips did from the ſhore depart?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:27887:8"/>Thou ſtriv'ſt to make thy crafty gueſt ſtill ſtay,</l>
                  <l>But he hoiſted up his ſailes and fled away.</l>
                  <l>Thou that to a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhips couldſt men transform;</l>
                  <l>Thy mindes affection couldſt not change nor turne.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſtriveſt to expell Loves cruell flame,</l>
                  <l>But Love did ſtill within thy Breſt remaine.</l>
                  <l>For'cis ſaid, that when <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> would be gon,</l>
                  <l>Thou to deteine him thus to ſpeake begun;</l>
                  <l>I doe not now intreate thee for to bee</l>
                  <l>My hu band, though that hope was once in me;</l>
                  <l>Though I deſerv'd to be thy wife hereafter,</l>
                  <l>Being a goddeſſe, and the bright Suns daughter.</l>
                  <l>Now to ſtay a while I onely thee deſire;</l>
                  <l>What leſſe canſt thou wiſh me that I ſhould require?</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt the Sea is rough, and thou ſhould feare it:</l>
                  <l>The Winde hereafter will ſtand for thee more fit.</l>
                  <l>Why wilt thou goe? <hi>Troy</hi> is not built againe,</l>
                  <l>Thou art not call'd theſe warres now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o mainetaine.</l>
                  <l>Here's love and peace, and it is onely I</l>
                  <l>That here am wounded by loves cruelty:</l>
                  <l>While thou in ſafety maiſt ſtay, and command</l>
                  <l>My Kingdome, which I offer to thy hand.</l>
                  <l>When ſhe theſe words had poſſionately to him ſaid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> preſently his Anchor waighd</l>
                  <l>So that the North-wind drove his ſailes away,</l>
                  <l>And her words, which vainely pleaded for his ſtay.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Cerces</hi> furious love began to rage;</l>
                  <l>So that ſhe ſought by art how to aſſwage</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:27887:9"/>With her accuſtom'd charmes her inward flame,</l>
                  <l>But yet they could not mitigate Loves paine.</l>
                  <l>Therefore if thou expecteſt helpe from hence,</l>
                  <l>In charmes or love-cups put no confidence.</l>
                  <l>If ſome waighty occaſion make thee ſtay in <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Take then my councell, for this is my doome.</l>
                  <l>He hath a great ſtrength that at once can free</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe, and ſet himſelfe at liberty.</l>
                  <l>He that can doe thus, I'le admire his compo ſition,</l>
                  <l>And ſay, he needeth not my admonition.</l>
                  <l>But thou that loveſt, and wouldſt thy love forget,</l>
                  <l>Yet caniſt not, for thy helpe I here will ſet</l>
                  <l>Theſe Rules downe: Firſt, be ſure to thinke upon</l>
                  <l>Theſe wicked acts which thou and ſhe haſt done.</l>
                  <l>Lay all unto the charge of the poore Maide,</l>
                  <l>Let thy coſt beſtowed on her be before thee laid:</l>
                  <l>Thinke how ſhe hath got from thee this and that,</l>
                  <l>And yet her covetous mind is inſatiate.</l>
                  <l>Thinke how by her perſwaſions at the laſt</l>
                  <l>Thy houſe for her joincture thou haſt to her paſt,</l>
                  <l>Howſhe falſified her Oath which ſhe had ſwore,</l>
                  <l>And made thee lye oft-times even at her doore:</l>
                  <l>Thinke that ſhe loves ſome other, becauſe ſhe</l>
                  <l>Diſdaines to love, or be belov'd of thee.</l>
                  <l>And though ſhe will not grant thee loves delight,</l>
                  <l>Her Peramour enjoyes her every night.</l>
                  <l>Let theſe things deepely through thy ſenſes ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>And from hence take occaſion of diſlike.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:27887:9"/>And I would have thee uſe ſuch amplification</l>
                  <l>That may ſet forth her wrongs with aggravation.</l>
                  <l>For if thou doe begin once to repent,</l>
                  <l>"Thy wrongs will make thee ſtraightway eloquent.</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe to love a Maid was once inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>But ſhe prov'd not agreeable to my mind:</l>
                  <l>Yet like ſicke <hi>Podalirius</hi> I was cured</l>
                  <l>By my owne medicines which I had procured.</l>
                  <l>For I that am Loves Phyſitian, will not ſticke</l>
                  <l>To confeſſe that I my ſelfe for love was fick:</l>
                  <l>But by ſcanning my Sweet-hearts faults I cur'd my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>And by often doing ſo regain'd my health.</l>
                  <l>My Miſtreſſe hath, thought I, but a bad thigh,</l>
                  <l>And yet, to confeſſe the truth, I did but lye,</l>
                  <l>My Miſtreſſe armes are not ſo faire quoth I,</l>
                  <l>And yet, to confeſſe the truth, I did but lye.</l>
                  <l>Shee is low of ſtature, and inſatiate,</l>
                  <l>And hence I grounded my diſlike and hate.</l>
                  <l>And ſince Vertues unto vices are ſo neare,</l>
                  <l>Her Vertues vices to me did appeare.</l>
                  <l>Thus all her naturall gifts thou maiſt deface,</l>
                  <l>And let thy blinded Judgement her diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>If that ſhe be full-bodied, call her fat;</l>
                  <l>If ſhe be browne, then thou maiſt call her black:</l>
                  <l>And if that ſhe be ſlender in the waſte,</l>
                  <l>For leaneneſſe then find fault with her thou maiſt:</l>
                  <l>Thou may'ſt call her wanton, if well behav'd ſhe be:</l>
                  <l>If honeſt, a piece of cold ruſticity.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:27887:10"/>And often preſſe her that ſhe would but grant</l>
                  <l>To expreſſe that skill which thou know'ſt ſhe doth want.</l>
                  <l>If ſhe have no voyce deſire her to ſing:</l>
                  <l>If ſhe cannot dance, her unto dancing bring.</l>
                  <l>If that her ſpeech be homely, rude and courſe,</l>
                  <l>Then give her ſtill occaſion of diſcourſe:</l>
                  <l>And if her skill in Muſicke be not much,</l>
                  <l>Deſire her to give her Lute a gentle touch.</l>
                  <l>If that her ſteps and gate uncomely be,</l>
                  <l>Be ſure that thou doe make her walke with thee:</l>
                  <l>And if her breſts hang downe on either ſide,</l>
                  <l>Pull off the Tiffeny that doth them hide.</l>
                  <l>Then make her laugh if that ſhe have bad teeth,</l>
                  <l>If ſlender eyes, with ſad ſtories make her weepe.</l>
                  <l>And ſometimes to thy Miſtreſſe in a morning come,</l>
                  <l>Before ſhe be dreſt, or head tyres put on.</l>
                  <l>For what are Maides when that they are undreſt?</l>
                  <l>When they are in their cloathes, they are at the beſt.</l>
                  <l>With Pearles &amp; Gold they dreſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves with Art,</l>
                  <l>And the Maid is of her ſelfe even the leaſt part.</l>
                  <l>And then thou maiſt imagine thou haſt loſt</l>
                  <l>In this throng of cloaths the Maid whom thou lov'ſt moſt:</l>
                  <l>And like a witty Lover take delight</l>
                  <l>In a reſting manner to delude thy ſight.</l>
                  <l>Yet to this Rule too much credit doe not give,</l>
                  <l>For a careleſſe beauty many doth deceive.</l>
                  <l>When thy Miſtreſſe is painting of her ſelfe, then ruſh</l>
                  <l>Into her preſence and ſo make her bluſh:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:27887:10"/>Thou ſhalt finde her Boxes, and her colours there</l>
                  <l>With which ſhe makes her breſt ſeem white &amp; fair.</l>
                  <l>Her window will ſmell like to <hi>Phineus</hi> table,</l>
                  <l>So that to turne thy ſtomacke it will be able.</l>
                  <l>And now I purpoſe afterward to ſhew</l>
                  <l>What in the acts of <hi>Venus</hi> thou muſt doe,</l>
                  <l>That Love wherein thou takeſt ſuch delight,</l>
                  <l>May thereby b'abaniſht, and quite put to flight.</l>
                  <l>Many Rules for ſhame I muſt leave unexpreſt,</l>
                  <l>But by my words thou maiſt conceive the reſt.</l>
                  <l>For ſome of late my Bookes doe carpe and blame,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe my <hi>Muſe</hi> hath ſuch a wanton veine.</l>
                  <l>Let him diſgrace thoſe Workes which I have done,</l>
                  <l>So my <hi>Verſe</hi> may pleaſe, and through the World be ſung.</l>
                  <l>Envy detracted from great <hi>Homers</hi> Wit,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Zoilus,</hi> thou didſt get a name by it:</l>
                  <l>And ſacrilegious tongues have out of ſpight</l>
                  <l>Diſgrac'd his <hi>Lines</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Vir.</note> that did of <hi>Aeneas</hi> wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te.</l>
                  <l>Envy, winds, thunder, aime at, blow, and ſtrike</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things that are advanc'd to greateſt heig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>But thou that art diſpleas'd with our looſe veine,</l>
                  <l>Conceive each ſubject muſt have a fittſtreme.</l>
                  <l>Warres muſt be in <hi>Heroicke Verſes</hi> writ,</l>
                  <l>Not enterlac'd with pleaſant ſtrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of Wit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Anger</hi> becomes a high lin'd <hi>Tragedy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Acommon line a merry <hi>Comedy:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iambick Verſes</hi> ſerve to jeere a foe,</l>
                  <l>Whether they doe runne ſwiftly, or o'reflow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:27887:11"/>The Elegy doth ſing of quiver'd Love,</l>
                  <l>Even as thy Miſtreſſe curſt or kinde doth prove.</l>
                  <l>It would not become <hi>Callimachus</hi> to rehearſe</l>
                  <l>The praiſe of <hi>Achilles</hi> in his verſe:</l>
                  <l>Nor would <hi>Cydippe</hi> be a ſubject fit</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Homers</hi> full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine, and his ſtrength of wit.</l>
                  <l>Who can endure, that wanton <hi>Thais</hi> ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Acted in the play of <hi>Andromache.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Art is directed to ſuch as <hi>Thais</hi> be;</l>
                  <l>My wanton time is ſportive, and moſt free:</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Thais</hi> onely my Art hath a care,</l>
                  <l>Not thoſe that with a fillet bind their haire;</l>
                  <l>For if my muſe hath lively here expreſt</l>
                  <l>Her matter fitly in the way of jeſt:</l>
                  <l>My Muſe ſhall overcome thoſe that abus'd her,</l>
                  <l>And of a falſe crime, falſly have accus'd her;</l>
                  <l>Let envy burſt, my Muſe ſhall haue a name,</l>
                  <l>The more ſhe frownes, the more ſhall be her fame.</l>
                  <l>For envies hatred will encreaſe my fame:</l>
                  <l>Then enuy be ſure to croſſe me, for if I live,</l>
                  <l>I'le give thee more occaſion for to grieve.</l>
                  <l>For it will vexe thy heart (I know) to ſee</l>
                  <l>My Verſes famous with poſterity.</l>
                  <l>For as my fame encreaſeth, my deſire</l>
                  <l>Of fame encreaſeth, and ſtill mounteth higher,</l>
                  <l>Though my panting horſes now begin to climbe</l>
                  <l>The hill, they may reach to the top in time,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:27887:11"/>For Elegies are indebted unto me,</l>
                  <l>As much as Heroicks unto <hi>Virgil</hi> be.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ovids</hi> Remedy of Love.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HItherto we have anſwered envy, now againe</l>
                  <l>I will recall my ſelfe, draw in my raine;</l>
                  <l>And I the Poet will proceede to runne</l>
                  <l>On in that circle which I have begunne.</l>
                  <l>When thou art to performe the youthfull deed,</l>
                  <l>And that to lie with thee ſhe hath agreed;</l>
                  <l>And that the promiſ'd night is now at hand,</l>
                  <l>Wherein unto thy bargaine thou muſt ſtand:</l>
                  <l>Lye with ſome other, leaſt thou being ful of pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Thy Miſtreſſe doe requite thee with ſuch meaſure,</l>
                  <l>And anſwer thee againe, with ſuch ſweet height</l>
                  <l>Of dalliance that may take thee with delight.</l>
                  <l>On any one beſtow thy ſtrength of Love,</l>
                  <l>And thy next affection will more milder prove.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> is ſtill moſt powerfull at the firſt,</l>
                  <l>But heate ſeekes ſhades, and water quenches thirſt.</l>
                  <l>I am aſham'd, yet to ſpeake I will aſſay,</l>
                  <l>Joyne <hi>Venus</hi> ſhapes in an uncomely way:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:27887:12"/>Which may at any time be eaſily done,</l>
                  <l>For they ſuppoſe nought doth them miſ-become.</l>
                  <l>Then to ſet open the Windows I thee bid,</l>
                  <l>And by day-light marke thoſe parts that are hid.</l>
                  <l>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pleaſur's ended which thou hadſt deſir'd</l>
                  <l>And that thy minde and body both are tyr'd:</l>
                  <l>While thou repentſt that thou a maid didſt touch,</l>
                  <l>And reſolv'ſt nere againe to doe ſo much.</l>
                  <l>Then obſerve the faults that in her bodie are.</l>
                  <l>Looke on her when ſhe lies nak'd and bare.</l>
                  <l>If theſe rules ſeeme of ſmall uſe unto any</l>
                  <l>Though all availe not, ſome may being many.</l>
                  <l>The little Vipers biting ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls the Bull,</l>
                  <l>And a little hound the Boare will tugge and pull:</l>
                  <l>Of my precepts, being many, the belt take,</l>
                  <l>Many collected a great heape doe make.</l>
                  <l>But ſince ſo many men and mindes there are</l>
                  <l>To credit me in all things take no care;</l>
                  <l>For that which doth not offend us, may be thought,</l>
                  <l>Perhaps by another to bee a fault.</l>
                  <l>He that hath ſeene thoſe parts ſhould not be ſeene</l>
                  <l>His love will coole, though it hath furious beene.</l>
                  <l>He that hath ſeen when his ſweete-heart doth riſe</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Venus</hi> encounter and her Veneries,</l>
                  <l>What ſtaines and ſpots moſt ſhamefully are ſpred,</l>
                  <l>On the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olluted and defiled bed.</l>
                  <l>If theſe things can delight you, he will ſay,</l>
                  <l>Proceede you lovers, and ſtill ſport and play.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:27887:12"/>For when that Loves torch hath enflam'd your mind,</l>
                  <l>Your ſuddain heate then no diſlike can finde:</l>
                  <l>For when <hi>Cupid</hi> drawes his arrowes to the head,</l>
                  <l>The greater wounds of Love are thereby bred.</l>
                  <l>And then of Lovers, the wounded company</l>
                  <l>Require the greater care and remedy.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall we ſay of thoſe who have laine hid</l>
                  <l>In ſome ſecret corner, while their ſweet-heart did</l>
                  <l>Make water, and ſo by that meanes did ſee</l>
                  <l>Thoſe parts which for modeſty ſhould conceled be?</l>
                  <l>The gods forbid we ſhould ſuch rules invent,</l>
                  <l>Though they profit, yet they are not expedient.</l>
                  <l>But I adviſe thee for to have two Loves;</l>
                  <l>Hee that loves many, to none loving proves.</l>
                  <l>When Loue is ſo devided, then at length,</l>
                  <l>One Love abateth from the others ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>Great Rivers that within the full bankes glided,</l>
                  <l>Grow-leſle, being into ſmaller ſtreames divided</l>
                  <l>And if ſtickes be pull'd aſunder, then the fire</l>
                  <l>Doth ſtraight goe out, and the flame doth expire.</l>
                  <l>One Anchor cannot hold a ſtout ſhip faſt,</l>
                  <l>One hooke is not enough for to be caſt</l>
                  <l>Into the water: he that provides two things</l>
                  <l>Obtaines his ends and ſtill the victory wins.</l>
                  <l>Thou that unwillingly didſt one ſweet-heart ſerve,</l>
                  <l>Finde out another that may thy love deſerve.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minos</hi> forgot his love to <hi>Paſiphae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When he in loue with <hi>Progne</hi> needs would be.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:27887:13"/>
                     <hi>Alcinaeus</hi> did his <hi>Phegis</hi> love forget,</l>
                  <l>When he <hi>Callirhoe</hi> to his bed did get.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Paris</hi> ſtill had <hi>Oenone</hi> loved,</l>
                  <l>If the Whore <hi>Hellen</hi> be had not approved.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pandion</hi> of his wife <hi>Progne</hi> tooke care,</l>
                  <l>Till her Siſter <hi>Philomel</hi> did ſeeme more faire:</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould I more examples here unfold?</l>
                  <l>"Since a new Love makes men forſake the old.</l>
                  <l>A Mother for her childs death makes leſſe mone</l>
                  <l>That had many, than ſhe doth that had but one.</l>
                  <l>And doe not thinke that I new lawes doe mention,</l>
                  <l>Yet would it were the glory of my invention,</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Atrides</hi> who did all things ſee, this ſaw,</l>
                  <l>And was not all <hi>Greece</hi> by him kept in awe?</l>
                  <l>For he himſelfe was conquer'd by the looke</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Cryſes</hi> whom he in the warres had tooke:</l>
                  <l>But yet her father fooliſhly then wept,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he had her from <hi>Achilles</hi> kept:</l>
                  <l>Why doſt thou weepe old man for the happy fate</l>
                  <l>Of thy Daughter hindering ſo her happy ſtate?</l>
                  <l>For when <hi>Chalchas</hi> truſting in <hi>Achilles</hi> aide,</l>
                  <l>Had commanded that he ſhould reſtore the Maide,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Atrides</hi> ſaid, even ſhe that's next in fame,</l>
                  <l>And ſome letters tooke away hath the ſame name,</l>
                  <l>Her let <hi>Achilles</hi> yeeld me if he be wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Elſe he ſhall feele that power he doth deſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>If this action <hi>(Grecians)</hi> foule to you appeare,</l>
                  <l>Know that my ſtout hand doth the Scepter beare:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:27887:13"/>If I am King, then ſhe ſhall with me ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Elſe may <hi>Therſites</hi> all my Kingdomes keepe.</l>
                  <l>This ſaid, he had her in his firſt loves ſtead,</l>
                  <l>His new love cur'd the old, for ſtraight it fled.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Agamemnon</hi> did, looke thou doſt doe,</l>
                  <l>Put love into a maze by loving two.</l>
                  <l>If thou wovldſt know to get them, read our <hi>Arts</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Love,</hi> and thou ſhalt have choiſe of Sweet-hearts.</l>
                  <l>But if our Rules have any power to heale,</l>
                  <l>I <hi>Apollo</hi> doe his Art by me reveale.</l>
                  <l>Though thou burnſt as if <hi>Aetna</hi> did thee enfold,</l>
                  <l>Seeme to thy Miſtreſſe in affection cold:</l>
                  <l>Diſſemble thy paine, that thou maiſt her deceive,</l>
                  <l>And laugh then, when thou inwardly doſt grieve.</l>
                  <l>I would not have thee ſtraight way quench thy flame</l>
                  <l>That over thy affections thou maiſt raigne.</l>
                  <l>I command thee onely but to counterfeit,</l>
                  <l>As if thy former affection thou didſt quit:</l>
                  <l>And ſo by imitation thou ſhalt doe</l>
                  <l>That which thou faignedſt, really and true.</l>
                  <l>For oftentimes that I might ſo ſhun drinking,</l>
                  <l>I would counterfeit my ſelfe aſleepe by winking:</l>
                  <l>And while I in counterfeiting did proceed,</l>
                  <l>I many times have fallen aſleepe indeed.</l>
                  <l>So thoſe who cunning in counterfeiting are,</l>
                  <l>Doe ſeldome fall into Loves ſpring or ſnare.</l>
                  <l>The mind by cuſtome doth Love entertaine,</l>
                  <l>And it by cuſtome is forgot againe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:27887:14"/>He that can counterfeit himſelfe no Lover,</l>
                  <l>By counterfeiting ſhall his health recover.</l>
                  <l>Come if ſhe bid thee at the appointed night,</l>
                  <l>And if ſhee ſhut her doore, yet beare it light.</l>
                  <l>Doe not thou uſe ſoft complements, or prate</l>
                  <l>With flattering words, or ſcold before her gate:</l>
                  <l>Or if that ſhee doe lock thee out in ſpight,</l>
                  <l>Doe not thou at her threſhold lye all night:</l>
                  <l>Nor yet complaine unto her in the morning;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhew a ſigne of ſorrow for her ſcorning</l>
                  <l>Thy love: for when ſhe ſees thou doſt not grieve</l>
                  <l>For her diſdaine, ſhe her diſdaine will leave.</l>
                  <l>Thy Love will ceaſe, if thou thus careleſſe ſeeme.</l>
                  <l>The Horſe reſiſts the bridle when 'tis ſeene.</l>
                  <l>But uſe ſuch pretended ſhewes as I have bid,</l>
                  <l>"Good effects at firſt are in their cauſes hid.</l>
                  <l>Loves cure thus by a cloſe way ſhall be done,</l>
                  <l>"Since birds that ſee the nets, the nets doe ſhun.</l>
                  <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve her not ſtill when ſhee doth thee deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>If ſhee diſdaine thee let thy courage riſe.</l>
                  <l>If her gate ſtand open paſſe by though ſhe call,</l>
                  <l>On the appoynted night come not at all.</l>
                  <l>Patience will make thee to endure annoy,</l>
                  <l>And from thy ſufferings thou ſhalt receive joy,</l>
                  <l>There is no hardneſſe in my Rules or Art:</l>
                  <l>For of a Counſellour now I play the part.</l>
                  <l>And ſince mens mindes doe differ, and doe varie,</l>
                  <l>Our Art ſhall varie that may now miſcarry.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:27887:14"/>Since there are thouſand ſhapes of miſery,</l>
                  <l>There are thouſand ſalves to cure each miſery:</l>
                  <l>Some bodies muſt be lanc'd, and ſear'd, and cut,</l>
                  <l>And ſome by potions and hearbes health have got.</l>
                  <l>But if thou art of a more ſofter mind,</l>
                  <l>So that <hi>Love</hi> in his fetters doth thee bind,</l>
                  <l>And like a Conquerour holds thee at his beck,</l>
                  <l>And cruelly doth tread upon thy neck,</l>
                  <l>To ſtruggle with thy paſſion thou muſt ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>Let thy windes drive thy ſhip as they doe pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>I would have thee quench the thirſt of thy deſire,</l>
                  <l>And with ſome common water quench the fire.</l>
                  <l>And thou maiſt drinke farre more than will ſuffice,</l>
                  <l>Till full of water thou doſt it deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>With thy Sweet-heart take thy fill of delight,</l>
                  <l>And in her company ſpend both day and night:</l>
                  <l>For thy Love will end with ſuch ſatiety,</l>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt be able to want her company,</l>
                  <l>And tarry from her: hungry Love is tyr'd</l>
                  <l>With plenty, and doth loath what he deſir'd.</l>
                  <l>Be not thou jealous, jealouſie doth nouriſh</l>
                  <l>Love, and doth make it both to laſt and flouriſh.</l>
                  <l>If to extinguiſh Love thou haſt a care,</l>
                  <l>Extinguiſh jealouſie and idle feare.</l>
                  <l>He that fears his Miſtreſſe ſhould be taken from him,</l>
                  <l>There is no remedy can worke upon him.</l>
                  <l>The Mother for that ſonne doth take moſt care,</l>
                  <l>Of whoſe returne from the wars ſhe ſtands in feare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:27887:15"/>Neare the Colline Gate a Temple there doth ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Which is from <hi>Erix</hi> called, and ſo nam'd:</l>
                  <l>There love they, in the <hi>Lethaean</hi> waves they drench,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Cupids</hi> torches in thoſe waters quench.</l>
                  <l>There young-men pray, they may their lovesforget,</l>
                  <l>That on diſdainefull Maides their love have ſet:</l>
                  <l>But at the laſt, thus <hi>Cupid</hi> ſaid to me;</l>
                  <l>(Elſe 'twas a dreame, a dreame it well might be)</l>
                  <l>O thou, who teacheſt men how they ſhould love:</l>
                  <l>And teacheſt them the remedy to remove</l>
                  <l>Their paſſion: <hi>Ovid</hi> adde theſe rules of mine</l>
                  <l>Unto thoſe preceps, and thoſe rules of thine:</l>
                  <l>Thinke on thy troubles and thy miſery,</l>
                  <l>The thought of croſſes will make love to flye:</l>
                  <l>"And God doch never none ſo intirely bleſſe,</l>
                  <l>"But that he gives them troubles more or leſſe.</l>
                  <l>He that hath ſuits or feareth his rent day,</l>
                  <l>Is wreſted with a debt which he muſt pay.</l>
                  <l>He that hath a hard father, that doth keepe him in,</l>
                  <l>Let him thinke on his father, though unſeene.</l>
                  <l>If thou ſeeſt a marryed man in a poore eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Thinke that his wife doth cauſe his hapleſſe fate.</l>
                  <l>If thou in the Country a fruitfull Vineyard haſt,</l>
                  <l>Take care leſt ill winds ſhould thy rich Grapes blaſt.</l>
                  <l>If he have a ſhip that is returning home,</l>
                  <l>Let him thinke what loſſes oft by Sea doe come.</l>
                  <l>A Sonne at the Warres to trouble thee may be able,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe a Daughter that is marrigeable.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:27887:15"/>"What actions to our life belonging are,</l>
                  <l>"But will afford us cauſe of griefe and care.</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Paris</hi> had remembred his brothers fate,</l>
                  <l>Their deaths had made him <hi>Hellena</hi> to hate:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Cupid</hi> more unto me then had ſpake,</l>
                  <l>But that out of my dreame I then did wake.</l>
                  <l>For when my dreame (ſure 'twas a dream) had left me,</l>
                  <l>My waking thus, of many Rules bereft me:</l>
                  <l>Yet will I ſtill goe on, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forſake</l>
                  <l>My intended courſe, till I an end doe make.</l>
                  <l>Let Lovers take heede of ſolitude, they may be</l>
                  <l>Safer, if they frequent good company:</l>
                  <l>For thoughts of Love by being alone increaſe;</l>
                  <l>But if thou keepe company, then they will ceaſe.</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt be ſad, if that thou art alone,</l>
                  <l>Thy Miſtreſſe beauty into thy minde will come.</l>
                  <l>And thus the nights are, then the dayes more ſad,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe no company can then be had.</l>
                  <l>Shun not diſcourſe, nor ſhut thy chamber doore,</l>
                  <l>Nor in the darke, thy ſelfe with teares deplore.</l>
                  <l>And have ſome <hi>Pylades,</hi> that may cure <hi>Oreſtes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This uſe of friendſhip' mongſt others not the leaſt is.</l>
                  <l>What did hurt <hi>Phyllis,</hi> but that ſhe did love</l>
                  <l>To frequent the Wood, and ſolitary Grove?</l>
                  <l>What cauſed her by her owne hands to dye,</l>
                  <l>But ſollitude, and want of company?</l>
                  <l>For like to <hi>Bacchus</hi> Nimphs through griefe and care</l>
                  <l>She was wont to goe with looſe diſheaveld haire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:27887:16"/>And ſometimes looking to the Sea ſhe would ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes being weary lye downe on the ſand.</l>
                  <l>Faithleſſe <hi>Demophoon,</hi> full of treachery;</l>
                  <l>Faithleſſe <hi>Demophoon</hi> ſhe aloud did cry</l>
                  <l>To the deafe waves, that 'gainſt the ſhoares did breake,</l>
                  <l>While ſobs did breake off thoſe words ſhe did ſpeak.</l>
                  <l>There was a narrow path cover'd with a ſhade,</l>
                  <l>By which to the Sea ſhe oft her journey made:</l>
                  <l>Her miſerable ſteppes had even worne</l>
                  <l>This new way walking on't as one forlorne:</l>
                  <l>And with a pale countenance being hither come,</l>
                  <l>Upon her ſilken girdle ſhe looketh downe:</l>
                  <l>She looks upon the bonghes, doubts, and doth feare,</l>
                  <l>And to doe what ſhee deſired, ſhe doth not dare.</l>
                  <l>At laſt her fingers about her neck did knit</l>
                  <l>A halter and ſo hangd her ſelfe with it.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Phyllis!</hi> hadſt thou not beene alone,</l>
                  <l>The woods for <hi>Phyllis</hi> had not made ſuch mone.</l>
                  <l>For every wood ſuch griefe for thee conceives,</l>
                  <l>That for thee each yeare it mourns without Leaves,</l>
                  <l>Le maids and men by <hi>Phyllis</hi> example take;</l>
                  <l>Beware of being alone for <hi>Phyllis</hi> ſake.</l>
                  <l>There was a yong man that had almoſt done</l>
                  <l>What my Muſe preſcribes, &amp; to his health was come:</l>
                  <l>But while that he kept company with each Lover,</l>
                  <l>Hee loſt that health he did before recover:</l>
                  <l>And Love did take againe his Golden Dart,</l>
                  <l>And ſhot this young man deeply to the heart.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:27887:16"/>If thou doſt love, and wouldſt not love, then ſee</l>
                  <l>That thou doe ſhunne all amorous company.</l>
                  <l>For unto Cattell this much hurt hath done,</l>
                  <l>Who from each other take infection.</l>
                  <l>Their Eyes, that looke on bad eyes, are hurt by it,</l>
                  <l>Bodies to bodies infection doe tranſmit.</l>
                  <l>And ſometimes a Riverthat's hard by doth flow,</l>
                  <l>And moiſten places that are dry in ſhow.</l>
                  <l>So love concealed through thy veines will glide,</l>
                  <l>If with thy Miſtreſſe thou doſt ſtill abide:</l>
                  <l>And in framing excuſes we all witty be,</l>
                  <l>That we may enjoy our Miſtreſſe company.</l>
                  <l>Another too was cured, but his paine</l>
                  <l>Renew'd by living neere to her againe:</l>
                  <l>His wounds of Love once heal'd, did bleed afreſh,</l>
                  <l>And ſo my Art thereby had no ſucceſſe.</l>
                  <l>If fire be neere a houſe, 'twill ſoone take fire:</l>
                  <l>Keepe from thoſe places that may ſtirre deſire.</l>
                  <l>For if that ſhee within the Cloyſters walke,</l>
                  <l>Goe not unto her, nor yet with her talke:</l>
                  <l>For why ſhouldſt thou by talking with her againe,</l>
                  <l>Thy warme love with the heate of love enflame?</l>
                  <l>If thou art hungry, thou wilt not refraine</l>
                  <l>When meat's before thee, to fall to againe:</l>
                  <l>And when the water ſprings up in thy ſight,</l>
                  <l>To ſee it ſpring up will thy thirſt incite.</l>
                  <l>The Bull that ſees a Cow, follows her ſtraight way:</l>
                  <l>The Horſe that ſees a Mare, after her will neigh.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:27887:17"/>Yet love will not leave thee though this courſe thou take</l>
                  <l>'Tis not enough that thou doſt her forſake:</l>
                  <l>But bid her Mother, Siſter, Nurſe, farewell,</l>
                  <l>And whoſoe'r doth with thy Miſtreſſe dwell.</l>
                  <l>Her ſervant and waiting-maid both ſhunne.</l>
                  <l>If with commendation to thee they doe come</l>
                  <l>From thy Miſtreſſe, and doe with a feigned teare</l>
                  <l>Deliver it, their words doe thou not heare:</l>
                  <l>Nor how ſhe does ſee that thou doe not aske,</l>
                  <l>Of this ſilence thou wilt find the good at laſt:</l>
                  <l>And thou that of thy Miſtreſſe doeſt complaine,</l>
                  <l>Ceaſe thy complaints, they doe increaſe thy flame.</l>
                  <l>Thy love through ſilence better will expire,</l>
                  <l>A ſilent ſuffering will quench thy deſire.</l>
                  <l>In ſilence ſtrive thy affection to removed.</l>
                  <l>Who ſaith too oft he doth not love, doth love;</l>
                  <l>For flames of love are by degrees expell'd,</l>
                  <l>It is a wound that muſt be ſlowly heal'd.</l>
                  <l>Torrents more ſwiftly run than Rivers deepe,</l>
                  <l>Yet this is ſhallow, that one courſe doth keepe:</l>
                  <l>For love by ſrealth away from Lovers flyes,</l>
                  <l>And by degrees it languiſhes and dyes.</l>
                  <l>Yet never hate that Maid whom thou didſt wooe,</l>
                  <l>Such diſpoſitions ſavage beaſts doe ſhew.</l>
                  <l>He is not cur'd that endeth love with hate,</l>
                  <l>For ſtill he loves, though he doth her forſake.</l>
                  <l>They that were Lovers once, ſhould not turne foes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Appias</hi> doth hate ſuch diſſentions as thoſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:27887:17"/>For Love thus to inſinuate doth uſe,</l>
                  <l>And makes us love thoſe whom we doe accuſe:</l>
                  <l>And wandring Love hath found out an invention</l>
                  <l>To beget love by wrangling and diſſention.</l>
                  <l>A young man ſtood by his ſweet-hearts bed-ſide,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe began to threaten him, and chide:</l>
                  <l>Whereat in being ready away to goe,</l>
                  <l>She bid him draw the Curtaines, he did ſo;</l>
                  <l>Which as ſoone as he had ignorantly done,</l>
                  <l>He ſaw his wife, then he grew mute and dumbe.</l>
                  <l>But yet at laſt embracing her, quoth he,</l>
                  <l>Pardon my errour, thou haſt conquer'd me,</l>
                  <l>And ſo from her he did depart in peace.</l>
                  <l>Though he were cheated yet all ſtrife did ceaſe.</l>
                  <l>Let her have thoſe gifts ſhe hath from thee obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>For by ſuch loſſes greater good is gain'd.</l>
                  <l>But if that you by chance with her doe meet,</l>
                  <l>Theſe Rules which I doe give you, in mind keepe.</l>
                  <l>Take courage, and expreſſe thy valour on her,</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Pentheſilea</hi> with thy weapon conquer.</l>
                  <l>Thinke on thy Rivall, and how often late</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt ſtood knocking at thy Miſtreſſe gate:</l>
                  <l>And for thoſe vowes which thou haſt often made,</l>
                  <l>Now puniſh her, let her be ſoundly paid.</l>
                  <l>Curle not thy haire, nor when thou com'ſt to ſee</l>
                  <l>Thy Miſtreſſe, let thy Dublet unbutton'd be.</l>
                  <l>Nor of other Maids take thou care to pleaſe any,</l>
                  <l>But let her be to thee in ſtead of many.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:27887:18"/>But now I'le ſhew what ſlacks the eure of love,</l>
                  <l>And you your ſelfe ſhall an example prove.</l>
                  <l>For we hardly ceaſe to love, when we beleeve</l>
                  <l>We are belov'd againe, and ſo deceive</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves; ſince we moſt credulous and apt be</l>
                  <l>To deceive our ſelves with our ſelfe flattery.</l>
                  <l>But unto oaths or words no credit give,</l>
                  <l>For what than they doth oftner us deceive?</l>
                  <l>Nor if thy Miſtreſſe weepe, yet be not caught</l>
                  <l>With teares, for ſhe her eyes to weepe hath taught.</l>
                  <l>Lovers minds are divers wayes beſieg'd and try'd,</l>
                  <l>Like a Rocke beaten with waves on every ſide.</l>
                  <l>Shew not the cauſes why thou doſt her leave,</l>
                  <l>Nor tell her why thou griev'ſt, yet cloſely grieve.</l>
                  <l>Tell her not of her faults whatſoe'r they are:</l>
                  <l>For if ſhe come to excuſe them, then beware,</l>
                  <l>For whatſoe'r her caſe is, you muſt know;</l>
                  <l>In thy owne cauſe ſhe will thee overthrow.</l>
                  <l>In ſilence beare all: for if thou doſt ſtand</l>
                  <l>To reaſon with a Mayd, and ſtill demand</l>
                  <l>Satisfaction for ſome wrong thou didſt ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt ſcold thy ſelfe in love at laſt againe.</l>
                  <l>Yet to clip <hi>Cupids</hi> wings is not my intent,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall his Bow by my Art be unbent:</l>
                  <l>It is councell unto you which I doe ſing,</l>
                  <l>Therefore obey thoſe Rules which I doe bring.</l>
                  <l>And bright <hi>Apollo</hi> as thou ſtill haſt done,</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſt my worke that it may yet goe on.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:27887:18"/>
                     <hi>Phoebus</hi> is preſent; harke, me thinkes I heare</l>
                  <l>His ſounding Harpe; <hi>Phoebus'</hi> is preſent here:</l>
                  <l>In his reſplendant robe I have him eſpy'd,</l>
                  <l>Richer than robes in <hi>Tyrian</hi> Purple dy'd.</l>
                  <l>You then that are in love, ſee you compare</l>
                  <l>Your Miſtreſſes to thoſe that are more faire.</l>
                  <l>Each goddeſſe unto <hi>Paris</hi> faire did ſeeme;</l>
                  <l>But comparing their beauties, he did then eſteeme</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> the faireſt: Thus let every lover</l>
                  <l>Compare his miſtreſſe beauty with ſome other.</l>
                  <l>And ſo with others thou maiſt compare her mind.</l>
                  <l>Let not affection thy judgement blinde.</l>
                  <l>Briefe are the Rules I ſhall hereafter ſing,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſuch, as unto many helpe did bring.</l>
                  <l>And I have found the power of my owne Art,</l>
                  <l>Which when I was in love did eaſe my ſmart.</l>
                  <l>Keepe not thy Miſtreſſe letters, nor them read;</l>
                  <l>Much harme from reading letters doth proceed:</l>
                  <l>Put them into the flame, and ſay this fire</l>
                  <l>Shall burne this letter kindling my deſire.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſtias</hi> in a brand her ſonne did burne,</l>
                  <l>To burne a trecherous letter wilt thou mourne?</l>
                  <l>Remoove her picture; why ſhouldſt thou be tooke</l>
                  <l>With the faire ſhadow of a beauteous looke?</l>
                  <l>And alſo ſee that thou doſt ſhun thoſe places,</l>
                  <l>That are guilty of your amorous embraces.</l>
                  <l>For when thou thoſe places doſt behold and view,</l>
                  <l>Paſt pleaſures will thy preſent griefe renew.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:27887:19"/>Thinke not thus with thy ſelfe, here ſhe and I</l>
                  <l>Have beene together, here did together lye:</l>
                  <l>Here on this bed we ſlept, both with delight,</l>
                  <l>And I enjoyd her here one happy night.</l>
                  <l>Such thoughts as theſe doe but renew our flame,</l>
                  <l>And make the wound of love to bleede againe.</l>
                  <l>For as a Brimſton match will new life give</l>
                  <l>To dying cinders, making them revive,</l>
                  <l>And as one ſparke may kindle a great fire,</l>
                  <l>So one ſparke of love may enflame thy deſire.</l>
                  <l>So unleſſe thou endeavour to ſhun all</l>
                  <l>Occaſions, that thy love to minde may call,</l>
                  <l>Thy flame of love which ſeemed to expire,</l>
                  <l>Will burne againe in thee with freſh deſire.</l>
                  <l>The Sea-man rejoyceth when he hath ſaild by</l>
                  <l>A dangerous Rocke which in his way doth lye.</l>
                  <l>But take heed of thoſe places which appeare</l>
                  <l>Pleaſant, becauſe thou hadſt thy pleaſure there:</l>
                  <l>Theſe places Rocks to ſhipwrack thee become,</l>
                  <l>And as <hi>Carybdis</hi> ſee thou doe them ſhun.</l>
                  <l>And in ſome things, we can but adviſe our beſt,</l>
                  <l>And muſt commit to fortune all the reſt</l>
                  <l>For love when it is pooreſt, is moſt wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Riches and wealth doe ſeeme to blinde his eyes.</l>
                  <l>Poore men in Love oft-times more wiſedome ſhow,</l>
                  <l>For Riches doe make Love a wanton grow.</l>
                  <l>Why did none of poore <hi>Hecale</hi> a Wife make?</l>
                  <l>Why did none <hi>Irus</hi> for a Husband take?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:27887:19"/>For this, the Mayd was poore, and therefore tarry'd:</l>
                  <l>So was the other poore, and ſo not marry'd.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, the Theaters doe not thou frequent,</l>
                  <l>While in thy breſt love is not reſident:</l>
                  <l>For while thou hear'ſt their Songs and Muſick often,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeſt their Dances, theſe the mind doe ſoften.</l>
                  <l>There fained Lovers oftentimes advance</l>
                  <l>Themſelves, and in a Maske doe meet and dance.</l>
                  <l>Actors doe ſhew the Lovers cunning ſlight,</l>
                  <l>And their ſhewing of it ſtirres up a delight.</l>
                  <l>Read not <hi>Callimachus</hi> who of love doth write,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Cous</hi> who doth in that ſtraine endite.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sappho</hi> hath made me love my Miſtreſſe better,</l>
                  <l>And the <hi>Teian Muſe</hi> hath made my love waxe greater.</l>
                  <l>Who can with ſafety read <hi>Tibullus Verſe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or thoſe which <hi>Cinthia's</hi> Lover doth rehearſe?</l>
                  <l>Who that reads <hi>Gallus</hi> Verſes doth not melt?</l>
                  <l>And ſome by mine the like effects have felt.</l>
                  <l>For unleſſe <hi>Apollo</hi> doe fruſtrate my labour,</l>
                  <l>There are no Love-lines can like mine get favour.</l>
                  <l>Though there be ſome that faine would imitate me,</l>
                  <l>Yet beleeve that none are Rivals unto thee.</l>
                  <l>The more <hi>Hermione</hi> was lov'd of another,</l>
                  <l>The more <hi>Oreſtes</hi> did begin to love her.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Menelaus</hi> griev'd not when to <hi>Creete</hi> he went,</l>
                  <l>And though his wife was abſent, was content:</l>
                  <l>But when he ſaw that <hi>Paris</hi> ſtole her had,</l>
                  <l>Then for his wife he raged, and grew mad.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:27887:20"/>"Thoſe that love not their wives, yet when they ſee</l>
                  <l>"Another love their wives, they jealous be.</l>
                  <l>This bred <hi>Achilles</hi> griefe and ſad annoy,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe that <hi>Agamemnon</hi> ſhould her enjoy:</l>
                  <l>He wept, nor did he onely weepe it did ſeeme,</l>
                  <l>But ſomething did, or elſe he had ſlothfull beene.</l>
                  <l>Truely although my wiſedome be not much,</l>
                  <l>I thinke that I my ſelfe have done as much:</l>
                  <l>For out of envy to him he did receive</l>
                  <l>Her firſt fruits, and the next to him did leave.</l>
                  <l>Though that he ne're toucht <hi>Bryſis</hi> he doth ſweare</l>
                  <l>By his Scepter, his Scepter was no God to heare.</l>
                  <l>Then ſtill paſſe by thy forſaken Miſtreſſe gate,</l>
                  <l>And let thy quick ſteps thence convey thee ſtreight:</l>
                  <l>And ſure thou maiſt performe it, if thy mind</l>
                  <l>Doe gather ſtrength, and be thereto inclin'd.</l>
                  <l>For when thou paſſeſt by, goe quicke and faſt,</l>
                  <l>Spurre on thy ſelfe as if thou wert in haſte.</l>
                  <l>Thinke that the <hi>Syrens</hi> in that houſe doe dwell,</l>
                  <l>And make haſte from her, ſo ſhall all be well:</l>
                  <l>And for thy Rivall never grieved be,</l>
                  <l>Eſteeme him not now as thy enemy:</l>
                  <l>Or ſalute him though thy hatred doe remaine:</l>
                  <l>For'tis a ſigne thou art thy ſelfe againe.</l>
                  <l>And that I may play the Phyſitians part,</l>
                  <l>What meats to uſe I will preſcribe by Art.</l>
                  <l>For Scallions from <hi>Lybia</hi> ſent to thee,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe from <hi>Megaris</hi> both hurtfull be:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:27887:20"/>And luſtfull Eringoe's ſee that thou doe ſhun,</l>
                  <l>Which unto Venery make the body prone.</l>
                  <l>Rather eate Rue that ſharpeneth the ſight,</l>
                  <l>And that which hindreth <hi>Venus</hi> ſoft delight.</l>
                  <l>If concerning Wine thou wouldſt have me to ſhew</l>
                  <l>Some Rules, my Rules at this time ſhall be few.</l>
                  <l>Wine doth prepare the minde to Venerie,</l>
                  <l>Unleſſe you drinke too much, and drunken be:</l>
                  <l>For too much Wine the affections ſtupeſie,</l>
                  <l>When that the heart in Wine doth buried lie,</l>
                  <l>For as by blowing a fire may be kindled,</l>
                  <l>So by blowing a new fire may be extinguiſh'd.</l>
                  <l>A gentle winde doth nouriſh the weake flame,</l>
                  <l>A violent puffe doth put it out againe.</l>
                  <l>Drinke ſo much Wine as may thy cares expell,</l>
                  <l>If thou drinkſt more or leſſe, thou doſt not well.</l>
                  <l>This worke is done, now with freſh Garlands Crown</l>
                  <l>My Ship which to the intended Haven's come,</l>
                  <l>And to your ſacred Poet offerings give,</l>
                  <l>You Lovers that from hence did helpe receive.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
